I'd like to ask you,
أود أن أسألكم
what do these three people have in common?
ما العامل المشترك بين هؤلاء الأشخاص الثلاثة ؟
Well, you probably recognize the first person.
من المحتمل أن تتعرفو على الشخص الأول
I'm sure you're all avid "American Idol" watchers.
. أنا متأكدة أنكم جميعا متابعون جيدون لبرنامج "أمريكان أيدول"
But you might not recognize Aydah Al Jahani,
أقد لا تستطيعون التعترف على عايدة الجهني
who is a contestant, indeed a finalist,
وهي مشاركة في الدور النهائي
in the Poet of the Millions competition,
في مسابقة شاعر المليون
which is broadcast out of Abu Dhabi,
التي تبث من أبو ظبي ،
and seen throughout the Arab world.
وتتابع في جميع أنحاء العالم العربي
In this contest
في هذه المسابقة
people have to write and recite
على الناس أن يؤلفوا ويلقوا
original poetry, in the Nabati form of poetry,
شعرا أصليا، في هيئة الشعر النبطي
And Lima Sahar was a finalist
وليما صحار كانت متنافسة في النهائيات
in the Afghan Star singing competition.
في مسابقة نجم الأفغان الغنائية
Now, before I go any further,
الآن ، قبل أن أذهب إلى أبعد من ذلك ،
yes, I know it all began with "Britain's Got Talent."
نعم ، أنا أعرف كل شيء بدأ مع "بريطانيا لديها الموهبة".
But my point in discussing this
ولكن وجهة نظري في مناقشتي هذا الأمر
is to show you -- I hope I'll be able to show you
هو لأظهر لكم -- أتمنى ان أكون قادرة على أن أريكم
how these merit-based competitions,
أن هذه المسابقات المبنية على أساس الجدارة
with equal access to everyone,
مع المساواة في الوصول إلى الجميع ،
with the winner selected via voting by SMS,
مع اختيار الفائز عن طريق التصويت عبر الرسائل القصيرة ،
are changing tribal societies.
تغير المجتمعات القبلية.
And I'm going to focus on Afghanistan
و سوف أركزعلى أفغانستان
and the Arab world with the UAE,
والعالم العربي في دولة الإمارات
how they're changing tribal societies,
كيف انها تغير المجتمعات القبلية ،
not by introducing Western ideas,
ليس عن طريق إدخال الأفكار الغربية ،
but by being integrated into the language in those places.
ولكن عن طريق الإندماج مع اللغة في تلك الأماكن
It all begins with enjoyment.
كل هذا يبدأ من المتعة
Video: We are late to watch "Afghan Star."
(فيديو): نحن متأخرون لمشاهدة النجم الأفغاني
We are going to watch "Afghan Star." We are late.
سنذهب لمشاهدة النجم الأفغاني. لقد تأخرنا.
We are running late.
نحن نتأخر.
We must go to watch "Afghan Star."
يجب أن نذهب لمشاهدة النجم الأفغاني
Cynthia Schneider: These programs are reaching incredibly deeply into society.
هذه البرامج امتدت بشكل لا يصدق في عمق المجتمع
In Afghanistan, people go to extraordinary lengths
أفغانستان يبذل الناس جهودا استثنائية
to be able to watch this program.
ليكونونوا قادرين على مشاهدة هذا البرنامج
And you don't necessarily have to have your own TV set.
وليس من الضرورة أن يكون لديك تلفزيونا خاصا بك
People watch it all over the country
حيث أن الناس تشاهده في جميع أنحاء البلاد
also in public places.
و في الأماكن العامة أيضاً
But it goes beyond watching,
لكن الأمر يتخطى المتابعة
because also, part of this
، لأن هناك أيضا جزء
is campaigning.
الحملة الانتخابية
People become so engaged
حيث أن الناس تصبح متعلقة
that they have volunteers, just like political volunteers anyway,
لدرجة أن لديهم متطوعين ، تماما مثل المتطوعين في السياسية
who fan out over the countryside,
الذين يتوزعون في الأرياف,
campaigning for their candidate.
دعما لمرشحيهم
Contestants also put themselves forward.
.المتسابقون أيضا يرشحون أنفسهم
Now, of course there is a certain degree of ethnic allegiance, but not entirely.
الآن ، بالطبع ، هناك درجة معينة من الولاء العرقي ، ولكن ليس تماما.
Because each year the winner has come from a different tribal group.
لأنه في كل سنة كان الفائز من مجموعة قبلية مختلفة
This has opened up the door,
و هذا قد فتح المجال ،
particularly for women.
لا سيما للنساء،
And in the last season there were two women in the finalists.
وخلال الموسم الماضي كانت هناك امرأتان في التصفيات النهائية.
One of them, Lima Sahar, is a Pashtun from Kandahar,
واحدة منهم ، ليما سحر ، وهي من البشتون من قندهار ،
a very conservative part of the country.
وهي منطقة محافظة جدا في البلد
And here she relates, in the documentary film "Afghan Star,"
. وهنا ها هي تروي في الفيلم الوثائقي نجم الأفغان
how her friends urged her not to do this
كيف أن صديقاتها ألحّ عليها على عدم القيام بذلك
and told her that she was leaving them for democracy.
وأخبرنها كيف أنها تتركهم من أجل الديمقراطية
But she also confides that
. لكنها أيضا تكشف أنها
she knows that members of the Taliban
على علم بأن أعضاء في حركة طالبان
are actually SMS-ing votes in for her.
كانوا يرسلون الرسائل القصيرة كي يصوتوا لصالحها
Aydah Al Jahnani also took risks
عايدة الجهني أيضا خاطرت
and put herself out, to compete
وبذلت جهدا للتنافس
in the Poet of the Millions competition.
في مسابقة شاعر المليون
I have to say, her husband backed her from the start.
يجب ذكر أن زوجها كان داعما لها من البداية
But her tribe and family urged her not to compete
لكن قبيلتها وعائلتها ألحوا عليها بعدم المشاركة
and were very much against it.
و كانوا معارضين بقوة
But, once she started to win,
. ولكن ما أن بدات في الفوز
then they got behind her again.
حتى أنهم رجعوا لدعمها
It turns out that competition and winning is a universal human value.
فقد تبين أن المنافسة والفوز هو قيمة إنسانية عالمية
And she's out there.
وانها هناك
Her poetry is about women,
شعرها يدور حول المرأة
and the life of women in society.
وحياة المرأة في المجتمع.
So just by presenting herself
فمجرد أنها قدمت نفسها
and being in competition with men --
ووجودها في مسابقة مع الرجال
this shows the voting on the program --
وهذا يدل على التصويت على البرنامج
it sets a very important example for young women --
يضرب مثالا هاما جدا بالنسبة للشابات --
these are young women in the audience of the program --
هؤلاء الشابات في جمهور من البرنامج --
in Abu Dhabi, but also people in the viewing audience.
في أبو ظبي ، ولكن أيضا الناس في اجتذاب جمهور المشاهدين.
Now you'd think that "American Idol"
الآن كنت أعتقد أن "أمريكان أيدول"
would introduce a measure of Americanization.
من شأنه أن يعرض مقياسا للأمركة
But actually, just the opposite is happening.
ولكن في الواقع ، فإن العكس تماما يحدث.
By using this engaging popular format
باستخدام هذا التنسيق للمشاركة الشعبية
for traditional, local culture,
للتقليدية ، والثقافة المحلية ،
it actually, in the Gulf, is precipitating a revival
في الواقع ، في منطقة الخليج ، هو التعجيل بحدوث انتعاش
of interest in Nabati poetry,
من مصلحة في الشعر النبطي ،
also in traditional dress and dance and music.
أيضا في اللباس التقليدي والرقص والموسيقى.
And for Afghanistan,
وبالنسبة لأفغانستان
where the Taliban banned music for many years,
حيث حظرت طالبان الموسيقى لسنوات عديدة ،
it is reintroducing their traditional music.
هو إعادة تقديم ألحانهم و موسيقاهم التقليدية.
They don't sing pop songs,
أنهم لا يغنون أغاني البوب ،
they sing Afghan music.
إنهم يغنون الموسيقى الأفغانية.
And they also have learned how to lose gracefully,
وقد تعلموا كيف يخسروا باحترام ،
without avenging the winner.
دون انتقام الفائز.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No small thing.
هذا ليس شيئا قليلا.
And the final, sort of, formulation
والمباراة النهائية هي هيئة من صياغة
of this "American Idol" format,
هيئة برنامج "أمريكان أيدول"
which has just appeared in Afghanistan,
التي ظهرت للتو في أفغانستان ،
is a new program called "The Candidate."
هو برنامج جديد يسمى "المرشح".
And in this program, people present
و في هذا البرنامج يقدم الناس
policy platforms that are then voted on.
مناهج السياسة التي يتم التصويت عليها بعد ذلك.
Many of them are too young to run for president,
كثير منهم من أصغر من أن يخوضوا انتخاباتٍ رئاسية.
but by putting the issues out there,
ولكن من خلال عرض القضايا هناك ،
they are influencing the presidential race.
هم يؤثرون على السباق الرئاسي.
So for me, the substance of things unseen
فبالنسبة لي ، فإن جوهر الأشياء غير مرئي ،
is how reality TV is driving reality.
يكون كيف أن تلفزيون الواقع يقود الواقع.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)